Ramón Carulla
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ramón Carulla papers
1971-1996
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ramón Carulla
0.3 linear feet
The Ramón Carulla papers contain letters, photographs, printed material, an interview, sketchbooks, and artwork documenting the career of Cuban American painter Ramón Carulla.
Biographical Note
Ramón Carulla was born in Havana, Cuba in 1938. In 1946 he moved to Miami with his father to attend public school, returning to Havana in 1953 to complete his schooling. In 1963 he began painting and had his first one-man show in 1967 at the Bacardi Gallery in Miami, where he had settled two years earlier. Although his work was initially abstract Carulla had moved towards figurative art by the late 1970s.
Scope and Content Note
This collection dates from 1971-1996, comprises 0.3 linear feet, and provides scattered documentation of the career of Cuban American painter Ramón Carulla. The collection contains letters to Carulla from artists and others; writings by others for and about Carulla; the transcript of an interview with Carulla; photographs of Carulla, friends, and his artwork; two sketchbooks; a painting; and printed matter including exhibition announcements and catalogs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series:
Series 1: Letters and Biographical Material, 1971-1996 (box 1, 3 folders)
Series 2: Writings About Carulla and Interview, 1986-1995, undated (box 1, 3 folders)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1982-1994, undated (box 1, 2 folders)
Series 4: Photographs, 1980-1989, undated (box 1, 4 folders)
Series 5: Artwork, 1986-1994 (boxes 1-2, 3 items)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects:
Cubiles, Miguel -- Photographs; Cuevas, José Luis, 1934- -- Photographs; Mérida, Carlos, 1891- -- Photographs; Valerio, Andres -- Photographs
Subjects-Topical:
Art, Cuban -- Florida -- Miami; Expatriate artists -- Florida -- Miami; Artists -- Cuba; Cuban American artists; Cuban American art -- Florida -- Miami; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Florida -- Miami
Types of Materials:
Sketchbooks; Photographs; Mail art; Works of art
Names:
Blanc, Giulio V.; Cubiles, Miguel; Kundsen, Karen; Luís, Fernando
Provenance
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Ramón Carulla in 1997.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Letters and Biographical Material, 1971-1996, Series 1:; (box 1, 3 folders)
  This series contains letters to Carulla from friends and artists including Fernando Luis and mail art from Miguel Cubiles. There are also letters from others concerning business such as exhibitions and gifts of Carulla's work.
  - Résumé, circa 1996 (Box 1 (pam))
  - Letters from Friends and Artists, 1971-1996, undated (Box 1 (pam))
  - Letters Concerning Exhibitions and Other Business, 1987-1995 (Box 1 (pam))
- Writings About Carulla and Interview, 1986-1995, undated, Series 2:; (box 1, 3 folders)
  Essays on Carulla found here include The Men Under the Hats by Giulio Blanc, Ramón Carulla: The Delicate Look of Madness by Alicia M. Menendez, and an essay by Karen Kundsen of the Detroit Art Institute.
  - Essays on Carulla by Art Historians, 1992, 1994, undated (Box 1 (pam))
  - Poem, A Ramón Carulla, by Humberto J. Figueras, 1995 (Box 1 (pam))
  - Transcript (in Spanish) of an Interview of Carulla by Felix Beltran, 1986 (Box 1 (pam))
- Printed Material, 1985-1994, undated, Series 3:; (box 1, 2 folders)
  - News Clippings, 1985-1994, undated (Box 1 (pam))
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, and Press Releases, 1989-1994, undated (Box 1 (pam))
- Photographs, 1980-1989, undated, Series 4:; (box 1, 4 folders)
  Photographs of Carulla with friends and family include Miguel Cubiles, José Luis Cuevas, Andres Valerio, Carlos Mérida, and Carlos Carulla.
  - Carulla with Friends, Family, 1984, undated (Box 1 (pam))
  - Portraits of Carulla, 1980-1989 (Box 1 (pam))
  - Carulla Working and Artwork, circa 1983 (Box 1 (pam))
  - Carulla in an Interview, 1980 (Box 1 (pam))
- Artwork, 1986-1994, Series 5:; (boxes 1-2, 3 items)
  - Two Sketchbooks, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (pam))
  - Painting, The Last Look, 1994, (oil on paper) (Box 2 (sol))